/*****

Visual TrueType 6.1 Control Program 

The new control program allows for a much easier setup of cvts and their
hierarchy (inheritence) and exceptions (deltas) than the previous cvt and prep.
It is intended to declare
- cvt values
- relations between dependant (child) and independent (parent) cvts
- the ppem size below which child and parent cvts have the same values
- relative or absolute inheritence
- deltas for cvts in much the same way as deltas for control points in VTT Talk
- additional (user-defined) character groups
- spacing characters for user-defined character groups
- additional (user-defined) cvt categories
- global (font-wide) settings for
  - the range of ppem sizes at which instructions are on
  - the ppem size below which drop-out control is on
  - values for cvt cut-ins
- cvt attributes, last but not least, without using hexadecimal numbers...
All these declarations are compiled to the actual prep upon compiling the cvt.
*****/

/*
Additional Character group declarations

To declare additional character groups, such as for greek characters, use the
following example:

GROUP GreekUC
GROUP GreekLC
GROUP GreekFig
GROUP GreekPunct

This will introduce four new character groups: GreekUC, GreekLC, GreekFig, and
GreekPunct. These groups can then be used in the CharGrp.TXT template to
associate each character with its character group. Subsequently, when you
declare cvts, you can put the values for the Greek glyphs into the Greek group.
Finally, when you use the link tool on a Greek glyph, the tool will choose the
cvt from the Greek group.

Likewise, if you need more character groups for the Latin glyphs, such as for
small caps, superiors, or inferiors, feel free to add them. The limit is
currently 256, 8 of which are reserved and comprise the standard character
groups UpperCase, LowerCase, Figure, and Other.

Along with user-defined character groups, you may wish to define a series of
characters to check the spacing. The standard UpperCase group, for instance,
uses "HH HOHO OO   " and replaces all the blanks by the current glyph in the
main window displays this as the first part of the sample text at the top of
the window. Very likely, for other groups you will need a different sequence
of characters. Declare them as in the following example:

GROUP LatinUC		"HH HOHO OO   "

You can put any character between the double quotes on the right hand side.
If it's not on your keyboard, use the following syntax:

^574^ or ~414~

to enter the character's glyph index (between carets) or unicode (between
tildes), respectively.


Additional Feature category declarations

To declare additional feature categories, such as for flares, use the following
example


CATEGORY Flare

This will introduce a new character group Flare, which you may then combine with
all character groups, as shown further below.


Global settings

Following the user-defined character groups and feature categories are the
global (font-wide) settings. The range of ppem sizes at which instructions
are on is specified as follows:
*/

InstructionsOn @9..2047

/*
This compiles into appropriate code in the prep to turn off instructions below
9 ppem and above 2047 ppem. Feel free to change these numbers as you see fit.

The ppem size below which drop-out control is on is specified as follows:
*/

DropOutCtrlOff @144

/*
This compiles into approriate code in the prep to turn off drop-out control at
and above 144 ppem. The special value of 255 ppem means to do drop-out control
always. Users familiar with SCANCTRL and SCANTYPE may wish to control the bits
individually, hence as an alternative they may use the following pair of
assignments

ScanCtrl = 511
ScanType = 5

which would achieve the same goal.

The cvt cut-in values are specified as follows:
*/

CvtCutIn = 4, 2.5@29, 0@128

/*
This means that we want the cvt cut-in value to be
- 4 pixels for small ppem sizes in order to force distances to the cvt
- 2.5 pixels at medium ppem sizes (here starting at 29 ppem), and
- 0 pixels at large ppem sizes (here starting at 128 ppem), to give full
freedom to the actual widths.
Again, this compiles into appropriate code in the prep. You may wish to
experiment with the threshold ppem sizes and the pixel amounts, and you may
add a fourth setting inbetween, such as

CvtCutIn = 4, 2.5@29, 1@72, 0@128

or use only two, such as

CvtCutIn = 4, 0@128

whichever serves best.*/

ASM("WS[], 16, 0")

/* 
Syntax: ASM("WS[], 16, <accent threshold ppem>")
Uses: S[16] to store threshold value
Used by: FN 86, function to naturally space an accent above or below a base character.

Provides for sharper rounding of accent positions (FN 86) at lower sizes as determined by the threshold 
ppem.  A threshold value of zero means no threshold value is used. The threshold is an
inclusive value for which ppem values less than and equal to the threshold will not use RES style rounding 
of accent placment. Ppem values greater than the threshold will use RES style accent rounding.

Example: ASM("WS[], 16, 50"), will only use "softer" RES rounding of accent placement ABOVE 50 ppem.
*/

ClearTypeCtrl = 1

/*ClearTypeCtrl = 1. Enable native ClearType mode for all TrueType instructions, thus indicating a font 
that is ClearType aware (and hence the rasterizer should not e.g. bypass delta instructions)
If the parameter is set to zero, TrueType will not be in native mode. 
If the parameter is greater than zero it will be in ClearType native mode. */
 
LinearAdvanceWidths = 0

/*LinearAdvanceWidths permits to override the default usage of USE_INTEGER_SCALING flag 
in the flags field of the ‘head’ table. Acceptable values for n are 0 (default) 
and 1 (don’t use integer scaling). Non-integer scaling yields advance widths that are 
closer to the designed advance widths because it does not e.g. take 11 pt. at 96 dpi and 
round the resulting 14 2/3 ppem up to 15 ppem. Internal to the rasterizer e.g. MPPEM 
will still return an integer ppem size, but instructions keying off of this ppem size may 
no longer produce the same results. For instance, at 11 pt, 96 dpi 
(MPPEM rounds to 15 ppem from 14 2/3), the rasterization may get one pixel pattern, 
while at 15 pt, 72 dpi (or true 15 ppem), the rasterization may get a different pixel pattern, 
but since both ppem*/


/*Finally, the actual cvt numbers start. Recall from the dialog box entitled
"Edit cvt attributes..." that cvts have four different attributes
- character group
- link color
- link direction
- feature category
Instead of combining these four into a cryptic hexadecimal number, we now
spell them out in plain English. For example,

UpperCase
  Black
  X
  StraightStroke
    68: 192

introduces cvt number 68 with value 192 fUnits, with the combined attribute
UpperCase Black X StraightStroke. Once you have specified e.g. StraightStroke,
this part of the attribute remains in effect for all the following cvts, hence
you may wish to organize your cvts accordingly, as we did below. Same holds
true for the X, hence keep the X, but change the feature category to RoundStroke
and you get all UpperCase Black X RoundStroke cvts, etc. Indentation is optional
but may increase legibility; feel free to use as many blanks or tabs you like.

Lets start with the heights:
*/

UpperCase
  Grey
  Y
  SquareHeight
     2:     0           /* replace the 0 with the measured cap height */

 /* The following function, 89, rounds <cvt> depending on rendering 
environment and projection vector CALL[], <cvt>, 89*/

ASM("SVTCA[Y]") 
ASM("CALL[], 2, 89")

     8:     0           /* the baseline "height" remains 0 */
ASM("SVTCA[Y]")
ASM("CALL[], 8, 89")

  RoundHeight
     3:     0 ~  2 @50  /* replace the 0 with the measured cap height overshoot */
     9:    -0 ~  8 @50  /* replace the 0 with the cap base height undershoot */

/*
The ~2 @42 means the following:
- The 2 designates the parent cvt, which is the cap height in this case.
- The tilde designates a relative cvt value, which is the overshoot amount in
  this case. This amount will be used on top of the cap height.
- The 42 means that the overshoot should kick in at 42 ppem. Replace the 42 by
  whichever ppem size you wish the overshoot to kick in. 
*/

LowerCase
  SquareHeight
     0:     0 /* replace the 0 with the measured square ascender height */
ASM("SVTCA[Y]")
ASM("CALL[], 0, 89")

     6:     0 /* replace the 0 with the measured square x-height */
ASM("SVTCA[Y]")
ASM("CALL[], 6, 89")

/*The following sample delta, increases the lowercase x-height @22ppem*/
/*Delta (1 @22) */

    10:     0 /* replace the 0 with the measured lc_base height */

ASM("SVTCA[Y]")
ASM("CALL[], 10, 89")

    14:    -0 /* replace the 0 with the measured square descender height */

ASM("SVTCA[Y]")
ASM("CALL[], 14, 89")

  RoundHeight
     1:     0 ~  0 @50 /* replace the 0 with the measured round ascender height overshoot */
     7:     0 ~  6 @50 /* replace the 0 with the measured round x-height overshoot */
    11:    -0 ~ 10 @50 /* replace the 0 with the measured lc_base round height undershoot */
    15:    -0 ~ 14 @50 /* replace the 0 with the measured descender round height undershoot */

  Figure
  SquareHeight
     4:     0 /* replace the 0 with the measured square figure height */

ASM("SVTCA[Y]")
ASM("CALL[], 4, 89")

    12:     0 /* replace the 0 with the measured figure base height */

ASM("SVTCA[Y]")
ASM("CALL[], 12, 89")

  RoundHeight
     5:     0 ~  4 @50  /* replace the 0 with the measured round figure height overshoot */
    13:     -0 ~  12 @50  /* replace the 0 with the measured round figure height undershoot */

  Other
  SquareHeight
    16:     0
ASM("SVTCA[Y]")
ASM("CALL[], 16, 89")

    18:     0
ASM("SVTCA[Y]")
ASM("CALL[], 18, 89")

  RoundHeight
    17:     0
    19:     0

/*
Now we do the weights. We start with the grand parent cvt. Since the attributes
remain in effect for all the following cvts, and since the grand parent cvt does
not belong to a particular group etc., we reset the attributes as follows:
*/

AnyGroup
  AnyColor
  AnyDirection
  AnyCategory
    65: 0 /* replace the 0 with the actual weight of the grand parent cvt */

  X
    66: 0 = 65 @17 /* replace the 0 with weight of parent x distances */
  Y
    67: 0 = 65 @17 /* replace the 0 with weight of parent y distances */

/*
The = 65 @17 means the following:
- The 65 designates the parent cvt, which is the grand parent in this case.
- The equals sign designates an absolute cvt value. Unlike relative cvts, put
  the actual (absolute) amount here, not merely the extra (relative) amount,
  as it will not be added to the parent.
- The 17 means that the cvt may break lose from its parent at 17 ppem. Replace
  the 17 by whichever ppem size you wish this to happen. 17 ppem is merely the
  size at which a typical font will make the transition from 1-pixel-wide to
  2-pixel-wide stems.

Each cvt declaration can have a list of deltas. Using the above example:

    67: 150 /*= 65 @17 Delta (1 @17, -1 @31..36)*/

The Delta (1 @17, -1 @31..36) is optional and means the following:
- at 17 ppem we want to add 1 pixel to the weight of this distance
- at 31 ppem through (and including) 36 ppem we want to subtract 1 pixel
You can have more sizes, if you wish.

Now we start with the UpperCase characters
*/

UpperCase
  Grey
  X
  ItalicRun
    20: 0
  Y
  ItalicRise
    21: 0

/*
For italic fonts, we have to specify the components of the italic angle.
These are
- the italic run (how much across), and
- the italic rise (how much up).
You will have an italic rise for each character group, and you may have several
italic runs for each character group, to account for varying italic angles such
as in fonts like Garamond. For roman fonts, we don't need these cvts.

Next, we do the various strokes.
*/

UpperCase
  Black
  X
  StraightStroke
    68: 0 = 66 @27
    69: 0
  RoundStroke
    70: 0 = 68 @100
/*
    You can use relative inheritance for round strokes. For example,
    instead of the absolute distance you could use the difference
    between round and straight strokes, as was done for heights:
    
    70: 5 ~ 68 @100

    The 5 means the round stroke is 5 fUnits wider than the straight
    stroke (that is, cvt 68).
*/
    71: 0
  Y
  StraightStroke
    72: 0 = 67 @ 41
    73: 0
  RoundStroke
    74: 0 = 72 @100
    75: 0
  Diag
  StraightStroke
    76: 0 = 68 @ 41
    77: 0
  White
  X
  SerifExt
    78: 0
    79: 0
  Black
  Y
  SerifHeight
    80: 0

/*
Of course, SerifExt and SerifHeight are needed only for fonts that actually have
serifs. You can remove them for all other fonts.

We repeat the same pattern for the LowerCase characters. Again, ItalicRun and
ItalicItalic Rise are needed only for italic fonts
*/

LowerCase
  Grey
  X
  ItalicRun
    22: 0
  Y
  ItalicRise
    23: 0
  Black
  X
  StraightStroke
    81: 0 = 66 @ 27
    82: 0
  RoundStroke
    83: 0 = 81 @100
    84: 0
  Y
  StraightStroke
    85: 0 = 67 @ 41
    86: 0
  RoundStroke
    87: 0 = 85 @ 100
    88: 0
  Diag
  StraightStroke
    89: 0 = 81 @ 41
    90: 0
  White
  X
  SerifExt
    91: 0
    92: 0
  Black
  Y
  SerifHeight
    93: 0
  X
  Distance
    94: 0
  Y
    95: 0
  White
    96: 0

/*
Same pattern for the Figures...
*/

Figure
  Grey
  X
  ItalicRun
    24: 0
  Y
  ItalicRise
    25: 0
  Black
  X
  StraightStroke
    97: 0 = 66 @ 27
    98: 0
  RoundStroke
    99: 0 = 97 @ 100
    100: 0
  Y
  StraightStroke
    101: 0 = 67 @ 41
    102: 0
  RoundStroke
    103: 0 = 101 @ 100
    104: 0
  Diag
  StraightStroke
    105: 0 = 97 @ 41
    106: 0
  White
  X
  SerifExt
    107: 0
    108: 0
  Black
  Y
  SerifHeight
    109: 0

/*
...and all the other glyphs.
*/
Other
  X
  StraightStroke
    110: 0 = 66 @ 27
    111: 0
  RoundStroke
    112: 0 = 110 @ 100
    113: 0
  Y
  StraightStroke
    114: 0 = 67 @ 41
    115: 0
  RoundStroke
    116: 0 = 114 @ 100
    117: 0
  Diag
  StraightStroke
    118: 0 = 110 @ 41
    119: 0

/*
Here, you would add your own groups and individual cvts, as they are needed to
control a feature that several glyphs have in common.

Notice: To find out which is the next cvt number you can use, consult the
title bar of the control program. It indicates the number of entries in the cvt.
Since we start counting at 0, this is the same as giving you the next available
number.

CAUTION: Do not use cvt numbers in range 40 through 64. This range is used by
VTT internally.
*/